Well, Arthur C. Clarke,
حسناً , آرثر سي كلارك
a famous science fiction writer from the 1950s,
كاتب قصص خيال علمي شهير من خمسينات القرن الماضي
said that, "We overestimate technology in the short term,
قال " نحن نبالغ في تقدير التكنولوجيا على المدى القصير ,
and we underestimate it in the long term."
و نقلل من تقديرها على المدى الطويل "
And I think that's some of the fear that we see
واعتقد أن معظم الخوف الذي نراه
about jobs disappearing from artificial intelligence and robots.
عن اختفاء الوظائف بسبب الذكاء الاصطناعي والروبوت (الإنسان الآلي)
That we're overestimating the technology in the short term.
هو بسبب مبالغتنا في تقدير للتكنولوجيا على المدى القصير
But I am worried whether we're going to get the technology we need in the long term.
ولكني قلق ما إذا كنا سنحصل على التكنولوجيا التي نحتاج على المدى الطويل
Because the demographics are really going to leave us with lots of jobs that need doing
لأن التركيبة السكانية ستدفعنا إلى المزيد من الوظائف التي يتحتم القيام بها
and that we, our society, is going to have to be built on the shoulders of steel of robots in the future.
ونحن -مجتمعنا- سيتم بناءه على أكتاف الروبوتات الصلبه مستقبلاً
So I'm scared we won't have enough robots.
لذا أنا خائف من أن لا نمتلك أعداد كافية من الروبوتات
But fear of losing jobs to technology has been around for a long time.
ولكن ظل الخوف من فقدان الوظائف بسبب التكنولوجيا موجوداً منذ زمن طويل
Back in 1957, there was a Spencer Tracy, Katharine Hepburn movie.
ففي عام 1957 كان هناك فيلم سبينسر ترايسي و كاثرين هيبرن
So you know how it ended up,
وتعرفون كيف انتهى
Spencer Tracy brought a computer, a mainframe computer of 1957, in
احضرت سبنسر ترايسي حاسبوباً , حاسوباً كبيراً في عام 1957
to help the librarians.
لغرض مساعدة أمناء المكتبات
The librarians in the company would do things like answer for the executives,
وسيقوم أمناء المكتبات بأعمال مثل الإجابة على المديرين التنفيذيين
"What are the names of Santa's reindeer?"
ما هي اسماء غزلان الرنه الخاصه بسانتا
And they would look that up.
وسيبحثوا عن ذلك
And this mainframe computer was going to help them with that job.
وكان هذا الحاسوب الكبير سيقوم بمساعدتهم بذلك العمل
Well of course a mainframe computer in 1957 wasn't much use for that job.
وبالطبع لم يستخدم الحاسوب الكبير في عام 1957 لمثل هذا العمل
The librarians were afraid their jobs were going to disappear.
و أمناء المكتبة كانو متخوفين من اختفاء وظائفهم
But that's not what happened in fact.
في الحقيقة ماحصل هو
The number of jobs for librarians increased for a long time after 1957.
أن عدد الوظائف لأمناء المكتبات تزايد لوقت طويل بعد عام 1957
It wasn't until the Internet came into play,
حتى دخل الإنترنت في اللعبة
the web came into play and search engines came into play
كذلك مواقع الويب و محركات البحث دخلا في اللعبة
that the need for librarians went down.
فقلت الحاجة لأمناء المكتبات
And I think everyone from 1957 totally underestimated
واعتقد أن كل شخص من عام 1957 يقلل تماماً من
the level of technology we would all carry around in our hands and in our pockets today.
مستوى التكنولوجيا التي نحملها في ايدينا و جيبونا في الوقت الحاضر
And we can just ask: "What are the names of Santa's reindeer?" and be told instantly --
و نستطيع أن نسأل "ماهي اسماء غزلان الرنة الخاصة بسانتا ؟" ويتم إخبارنا فوراً
or anything else we want to ask.
أو أي شيء آخر نود السؤال عنه
By the way, the wages for librarians went up faster
وبالمناسبة ارتفعت أجور أمناء المكتبات بشكل أسرع
than the wages for other jobs in the U.S. over that same time period,
مقارنة بالوظائف الأخرى في الولايات المتحدة في نفس تلك الفترة
because librarians became partners of computers.
لأن أمناء المكتبات اصبحوا شركاء للحاسبات
Computers became tools, and they got more tools that they could use
واصبحت الحاسبات أدوات و حصلوا على المزيد من الأدوات التي يمكنهم استخدامها
and become more effective during that time.
و أصبحت أكثر فاعلية خلال ذلك الوقت
Same thing happened in offices.
و حصل نفس الشيء في المكاتب
Back in the old days, people used spreadsheets.
ففي الأيام القديمة الماضيه استخدم الناس جداول البيانات
Spreadsheets were spread sheets of paper,
فجداول البيانات كانت صحائف متفرقه من الورق
and they calculated by hand.
ويتم حسابها يدوياً
But here was an interesting thing that came along.
ولكن هناك شيء مثير جاء مصاحباً
With the revolution around 1980 of P.C.'s,
لثورة الحاسوب حوالي عام 1980
the spreadsheet programs were tuned for office workers,
ضُبطت برامج جداول البيانات لموظفي المكاتب
not to replace office workers,
ليس لإستبدالهم
but it respected office workers as being capable of being programmers.
ولكنها احترمت موظفي المكاتب بكونهم قادرين على أن يكونوا مبرمجين
So office workers became programmers of spreadsheets.
فأصبح موظفي المكاتب مبرمجين لجداول البيانات
It increased their capabilities.
فطورت قدراتهم
They no longer had to do the mundane computations,
فلم يعد عليهم القيام بالحسابات البسيطة
but they could do something much more.
بل القيام بشيء أكثر بكثير
Now today, we're starting to see robots in our lives.
في هذه الأيام بدأنا في رؤية الروبوتات في حياتنا
On the left there is the PackBot from iRobot.
على اليسار ترون باك بوت من آي روبوت ( سلسة من الروبوتات العسكرية )
When soldiers came across roadside bombs in Iraq and Afghanistan,
عندما صادف الجنود قنابل على جانب الطريق في العراق و أفغانستان
instead of putting on a bomb suit and going out and poking with a stick,
فبدلاً من ارتداء بدلة القنابل و تحريكها بعصا
as they used to do up until about 2002,
كما كان الحال حتى عام 2002
they now send the robot out.
في الوقت الحالي يرسلون الروبوت لعمل ذلك
So the robot takes over the dangerous jobs.
فهو يتولى الأعمال الخطرة
On the right are some TUGs from a company called Aethon in Pittsburgh.
و على اليمين بعضاً من التاقز من شركة تدعى إيثن في مدينة بيتسبرغ
These are in hundreds of hospitals across the U.S.
و يوجد المئات منها في مستشفيات الولايات المتحدة
And they take the dirty sheets down to the laundry.
فهم يقومون بإنزال الإغطية المتسخه إلى المغسلة
They take the dirty dishes back to the kitchen.
ويعيدون الأطباق المتسخه إلى المطبخ
They bring the medicines up from the pharmacy.
و يحضرون الأدوية من الصيدلية
And it frees up the nurses and the nurse's aides
فهم يحررون الممرضات ومساعديهم
from doing that mundane work of just mechanically pushing stuff around
من القيام بتلك الأعمال العادية من ميكانيكا دفع الأشياء فقط
to spend more time with patients.
إلى قضاء وقت أطول مع المرضى
In fact, robots have become sort of ubiquitous in our lives in many ways.
في الواقع اصبحت الروبوتس موجودة في كل مكان في حياتنا بعدة طرق
But I think when it comes to factory robots, people are sort of afraid,
ولكن أظن , تخاف الناس نوعاً ما عندما يتعلق الأمر بروبوتات المصانع
because factory robots are dangerous to be around.
لأنه من الخطر الإقتراب من روبوتس المصانع
In order to program them, you have to understand six-dimensional vectors and quaternions.
و حتى نتمكن من برمجتها يتعين علينا فهم ستة متجهات أبعاد و رباعيات
And ordinary people can't interact with them.
و لا يتسطيع الأشخاص العاديين التقاعل معهم
And I think it's the sort of technology that's gone wrong.
واعتقد أن ذلك النوع من التكنولوجيا ذهب على نحو خاطئ
It's displaced the worker from the technology.
فهي ابعدت العاملين عن التكنولوجيا
And I think we really have to look at technologies
واعتقد أنه يجب علينا ننظر في التكنولوجيا
that ordinary workers can interact with.
التي يستطيع العمال العاديين التعامل معها
And so I want to tell you today about Baxter, which we've been talking about.
وأ نا اريد أن اخبركم اليوم عن باكستر وهو ما كنا نتحدث عنه
And Baxter, I see, as a way -- a first wave of robot
و أرى باكستر كموجه أولى من روبوت
that ordinary people can interact with in an industrial setting.
يستطيع الناس العاديين التفاعل معها في ضبط المصانع
So Baxter is up here.
باكستر موجود هنا
This is Chris Harbert from Rethink Robotics.
و هذا كريس هابرت من Rethink Robotics.
We've got a conveyor there.
ولدينا ناقل هنا
And if the lighting isn't too extreme --
فإذا كانت الإضاءه غير قوية
Ah, ah! There it is. It's picked up the object off the conveyor.
ها هو يحمل الغرض قبالة الناقل
It's going to come bring it over here and put it down.
وسيحمله إلى هنا و ينزله
And then it'll go back, reach for another object.
وسيعود ليصل إلى غرض آخر
The interesting thing is Baxter has some basic common sense.
والشيء المثير هنا أن باكستر لديه بعض الحواس الأساسية الشائعة
By the way, what's going on with the eyes?
بالمناسبة ماخطب هاتان العينان
The eyes are on the screen there.
العينان موجودتان على الشاشة
The eyes look ahead where the robot's going to move.
فعندما يتحرك الروبوت تتحرك العينان إلى الأمام
So a person that's interacting with the robot
فالشخص الذي يتعامل مع الروبوت
understands where it's going to reach and isn't surprised by its motions.
يدرك إلى أين سيصل الروبوت فلا يتفاجأ بحركاته
Here Chris took the object out of its hand,
وهنا أخذ كريس الغرض من يده
and Baxter didn't go and try to put it down;
ولم يحاول باكستر أن ينزله
it went back and realized it had to get another one.
بل فهم أنه يجب عليه أن يجلب غرضاً آخر
It's got a little bit of basic common sense, goes and picks the objects.
فدليه القليل من الحواس الأساسية الشائعة التوجه لالتقاط الأشياء
And Baxter's safe to interact with.
و باكستر آمن في التعامل
You wouldn't want to do this with a current industrial robot.
فلا تريد أن تفعل ذلك مع روبوتات المصانع الحاليه
But with Baxter it doesn't hurt.
ولكن باكستر لا يؤذي
It feels the force, understands that Chris is there
فهو يشعر بالقوة و يفهم أن كريس يقف هناك
and doesn't push through him and hurt him.
ولا يقوم بدفعه أو إيذائه
But I think the most interesting thing about Baxter is the user interface.
وأظن أن الشيء المثير في باكستر هو الواجهة البينية للمستخدم
And so Chris is going to come and grab the other arm now.
سيقوم كريس بسحب الذراع الأخرى الآن
And when he grabs an arm, it goes into zero-force gravity-compensated mode
وعندما يسحبها ينتقل إلى وضع انعدام قوة الجاذبية المعادلة
and graphics come up on the screen.
و تظهر الرسومات على الشاشة
You can see some icons on the left of the screen there for what was about its right arm.
يمكنك أن ترى بعض الرموز في الجانب الأيسر من الشاشة لما كان سيفعل بالذراع اليمنى
He's going to put something in its hand, he's going to bring it over here,
فهو سيحمل شيئاً في يده وينزله هناك
And the robot figures out, ah, he must mean I want to put stuff down.
وسيكتشف الروبوت بالتأكيد هو يقصد أن انزل الأشياء
It puts a little icon there.
يضع علامة صغيرة هنا
He comes over here, and he gets the fingers to grasp together,
ويأتي هنا و يضع اضابعه ليمسك شيئاً
and the robot infers, ah, you want an object for me to pick up.
و يستنتج الروبوت -حسناً- أنت تريدني أن التقط غرضاً
That puts the green icon there.
فيضع علامة خضراء هنا
He's going to map out an area of where the robot should pick up the object from.
سيقوم برسم خريطة للمنطقة التي يجب على الروبوت التقاط الشيء منها
It just moves it around, and the robot figures out that was an area search.
سيحركها وسيفهم الروبوت أن هناك منطقة يجب البحث عنها
He didn't have to select that from a menu.
لم يحتاج إلى أن يختار ذلك من قائمة
And now he's going to go off and train the visual appearance of that object
والآن سينطفئ وسيتدرب على المظهر الخارجي للشيء
So as we continue here,
إذاً بينما نحن مستمرين
I want to tell you about what this is like in factories.
أريد ان اخبركم كيف يبدو ذلك في المصانع
These robots we're shipping every day.
هذه الروبوتس تُشحن يومياً
They go to factories around the country.
فهي تذهب إلى المصانع حول الدولة
This is Mildred.
هذه ميلدريد
Mildred's a factory worker in Connecticut.
ميلدريد هي عاملة في مصنع في ولاية كونيتيكت
She's worked on the line for over 20 years.
وعملت على الخط لمدة تزيد عن 20 سنة
One hour after she saw her first industrial robot,
وبعد ساعة من رؤيتها أول روبوت صناعي خاص بها
she had programmed it to do some tasks in the factory.
قامت ببرمجته ليقوم ببعض المهمات في المصنع
She decided she really liked robots.
وقررت أنها أحبت الروبوتس بالفعل
And it was doing the simple repetitive tasks that she had had to do beforehand.
وكان يقوم بالمهمات المتكررة التي كان يتعين عليها القيام بها سلفاً
Now she's got the robot doing it.
الآن لديها روبوت يقوم بها
When we first went out to talk to people in factories
عندما ذهبنا لأول مره للتحدث مع الناس في المصانع
about how we could get robots to interact with them better,
عن كيفية جعلنا للروبوتات تتفاعل معهم بشكل أفضل
one of the questions we asked them was,
أحد الأسئلة التي سألناهم
"Do you want your children to work in a factory?"
" هل تريد ان يعمل ابنك في المصنع "
The universal answer was "No, I want a better job than that for my children."
كانت الإجابة الموحدة هي " لا , أريد عملاً أفضل لإبني "
And as a result of that, Mildred is very typical
وكنتيجة لذلك , ميلدريد هي نموذجية
of today's factory workers in the U.S.
لعمال المصانع الحاليين في الولايات المتحدة
They're older, and they're getting older and older.
فهم أكبر سناً و يتقدمون في السن
There aren't many young people coming into factory work.
فهم ليسوا بعض الشبان الذين قدموا للعمل في المصنع
And as their tasks become more onerous on them,
وفي حين أن مهماتهم تزداد مشقة
we need to give them tools that they can collaborate with,
نحتاج أن نمنحهم الأدوات التي يمكنهم التعاون معها
so that they can be part of the solution,
بحيث تصبح جزء من الحل
so that they can continue to work and we can continue to produce in the U.S.
ليستمروا في العمل ولنستمر في الإنتاج في الولايات المتحدة
And so our vision is that Mildred who's the line worker
ورؤيتنا تتمثل في ميلدريد العاملة على الخط
becomes Mildred the robot trainer.
تصبح ملدريد مدربة الروبوت
She lifts her game,
فهي تترك لعبتها
like the office workers of the 1980s lifted their game of what they could do.
مثل موظفي المكاتب في ثمانينات القرن الماضي فهم تركوا لعبتهم في ماتمكنوا القيام به
We're not giving them tools that they have to go and study for years and years in order to use.
فنحن لن نعطيهم أدوات يتوجب عليهم دراستها لسنوات من أجل استخدامها
They're tools that they can just learn how to operate in a few minutes.
إنها أدوات يمكنهم تعلم كيفية تشغيلها في غضون دقائق
There's two great forces that are both volitional but inevitable.
هناك قوتان عظيمتان كلاهما إختياريتان ولكن لا غنى عنهما
That's climate change and demographics.
المناخ يتغير والتركيبة السكانية
Demographics is really going to change our world.
الديموغرافية ستغير عالمنا بالفعل
This is the percentage of adults who are working age.
وهذه نسبة البالغين الذين هم في سن العمل
And it's gone down slightly over the last 40 years.
و هي تتنازل بشكل طفيف خلال الأربعين السنة الماضية
But over the next 40 years, it's going to change dramatically, even in China.
ولكن خلال أربعون سنة ستتغير بشكل كبير حتى في الصين
The percentage of adults who are working age drops dramatically.
نسبة البالغين الذين هم في سن العمل تنازلت بشكل كبير
And turned up the other way, the people who are retirement age goes up very, very fast,
و تتحول لمسار آخر حيث ترتفع عند الأشخاص الذين هم في سن التقاعد بشكل سريع جداً
as the baby boomers get to retirement age.
وعندما يصل المواليد سن التقاعد
That means there will be more people with fewer social security dollars
هذا يعني أنه سيكون هناك المزيد من الأشخاص مع القليل من نقود الضمان الإجتماعي
competing for services.
يتنافسون على الخدمات
But more than that, as we get older we get more frail
والأشد من ذلك هو مع ازديادنا في العمر نصبح أضعف
and we can't do all the tasks we used to do.
ولا نستطيع القيام بالمهام التي كنا نفعلها من قبل
If we look at the statistics on the ages of caregivers,
فلو نظرنا إلى الإحصائيات عن اعمار مقدمي الرعاية
before our eyes those caregivers are getting older and older.
إنهم يتقدمون في السن أمام أعيننا
That's happening statistically right now.
وهذا يحدث إحصائياً الآن
And as the number of people who are older, above retirement age and getting older, as they increase,
وحيث أن أعداد الأشخاص الذين هم أكبر - فوق سن التقاعد و يتقدمون في السن - في تزايد
there will be less people to take care of them.
سيكون هناك اشخاص أقل يهتمون بهم
And I think we're really going to have to have robots to help us.
و اعتقد أنه سيتحتم علينا امتلاك الروبوتات لمساعدتهم
I mean robots doing the things that we normally do for ourselves
بل أعني أن الروبوتات تقوم بالأعمال التي نفعلها عادة لأنفسنا
but get harder as we get older.
ولكنها تزداد صعوبة مع تقدمنا في العمر
Getting the groceries in from the car, up the stairs, into the kitchen.
إحضار مشتريات البقالة من السيارة وصعود الدرج و وضعها في المطبخ
driving our cars to go visit people.
قيادة سياراتنا لزيارة الناس
And I think robotics gives people a chance to have dignity as they get older
واعتقد أن الروبوتات تمنح الفرصة للناس في الإحتفاظ بكرامتهم مع تقدم السن
by having control of the robotic solution.
من خلال السيطرة على الحلول الروبوتيه
So they don't have to rely on people that are getting scarcer to help them.
فلا يعتمدون على الأشخاص الذين تقل مساعدتهم لهم
And so I really think that we're going to be spending more time
و اعتقد أننا سنمضي أوقاتاً أكثر
with robots like Baxter
مع روبوتات مثل باكستر
and working with robots like Baxter in our daily lives. And that we will --
والعمل معهم في حياتنا اليومية و سوف
Here, Baxter, it's good.
هنا , باكستر أنه جيد
And that we will all come to rely on robots over the next 40 years
وسنعتمد على الروبوتات خلال الأربعين سنة القادمة
as part of our everyday lives.
كجزء من حياتنا اليومية
Thanks very much.
شكراً جزيلاُ
(Applause)
(تصفيق)